Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. Lee Pavao papers, 1960-1992 RL.11817
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. Lee Pavao papers
1960-1992
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Pavão, Lee
RL.11817
5.0 Linear Feet
Founded in 1864, the J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT) is one of the oldest and largest enduring advertising agencies in the United States. It is headquartered in New York. Lee Pavao was an advertising executive who served in a number of JWT offices before becoming President and CEO of JWT Brazil. The Lee Pavao papers include advertisements and advertising designs, clippings, correspondence, meeting minutes and planning documents, photographs, presentations, reports, slides, speeches and other materials relating to Pavao's career, primarily in Latin American offices in Brazil and Peru. Client companies represented include Ford, Kellogg and Kodak. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: Administrative Files; Presentations and Speeches; Photographs and Slides.
Biographical / Historical
Founded in 1864, the J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT) is one of the oldest and largest enduring advertising agencies in the United States. It is headquartered in New York. Lee Pavao was an advertising executive who served in a number of JWT offices before becoming President and CEO of JWT Brazil.
Lee Pavao was born in 1934 in Massachusetts. He attended the University of Massachusetts at Dartmouth (BS, Advertising Design, 1956) and joined JWT in New York, but was soon after drafted into the U.S. Army (1956-1958). Pavao returned to JWT New York (1958-1963) before being reassigned to a number of JWT's European offices (Amsterdam 1963-1965, Madrid 1967-1969) before returning to New York. Pavao spent the rest of his career in various JWT offices in Latin America (primarily Sao Paulo and Lima) before being named President and CEO of JWT Brazil in 1980, eventually assuming responsibility for JWT operations across Latin America. Pavao retired to Chapel Hill, North Carolina in 1988 where he became a community activist and member of City Council. He died in 2019.
Source: Obituary (https://chapelboro.com/news/obituaries/former-chapel-hill-town-council-member-lee-pavao-dies)
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The J. Walter Thompson Company. Lee Pavao papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2019.
Related Materials
Related materials may be found in the following Hartman Center collections:
J. Walter Thompson Company. Account Files
J. Walter Thompson Company. International advertisements
J. Walter Thompson Company. International Offices records
Collection Overview
The Lee Pavao papers include advertisements and advertising designs, clippings, correspondence, meeting minutes and planning documents, photographs, presentations, reports, slides, speeches and other materials relating to Pavao's career, primarily in Latin American offices in Brazil and Peru. Client companies represented include Ford, Kellogg and Kodak.
Advertising; Advertising -- Latin America.; Advertising agencies; Advertising agencies -- Management; Advertising executives; J. Walter Thompson Company; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; Eastman Kodak Company; Ford Motor Company; Kellogg Company
- Administsrative Files, 1960-1992; 1
  - Board of Directors, 1986-1988 (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors meetings, 1985-1988; 11 folders (Box 1)
  - Designs for gavel, 1960s (Box 8)
  - Don Johnston visit (Spanish, Portuguese), 1983 (Box 1)
  - European Managers Meeting, Madrid, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Epcot Advertising Forum, 1983-1984; 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Ford collateral literature (English, Dutch), 1962 (Box 1)
  - JWT America Latina Review, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Ford Latino Americano de Directores Creativos (Spanish), 1982 (Box 1)
  - JWT Archives Weekend--Honourably Retired Directors, 1990 (Box 1)
  - JWT Brasil Plan 1986-1988 (Box 1)
  - JWT Brazil 3-Year Plan, 1980 (Box 1)
  - JWT Brazil--Credentials, 1984 (Box 1)
  - JWT Brazil--Credentials, 1985-1986; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - JWT Brazil--Directory, 1981 (Box 1)
  - JWT Brazil--Marketing Plan, 1981-1983; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - JWT Brazil--Newsletter (Portuguese), 1982 (Box 1)
  - JWT Brazil--Reports, 1980-1986; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - JWT Group press kit, 1986 (Box 1)
  - JWT Guatemala, 1985 (Box 1)
  - JWT Latin America Review, 1986 (Box 1)
  - JWT Latin American Creative Forum certificate of participation, 1982 (Box 5)
  - JWT Managers' Guide to International Transfers (personnel policy), 1984 (Box 1)
  - JWT promotional merchandise price list, 1984 (Box 1)
  - JWT Mexico Marketing Plan 1981-1983 (Box 1)
  - JWT Peru--JWT News, 25th anniversary article, 1977 (Box 1)
  - JWT Peru--Presentation, 1983 (Box 1)
  - JWT Peru--Regional Management Review (Spanish), 1987 (Box 1)
  - Kodak creative (Spanish), 1970 (Box 1)
  - Latin American Ford Supervisors Conference, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Latin American Managers Meeting, 1981-1984; 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Latin American Managers Meeting, 1982-1984; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Memos, 1987-1989; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Print advertisements, 1960s; 6 folders (Box 8)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes: Alcan; Alianza para el Progreso (Spanish); Chesterfield and Winfield cigarettes (Dutch); Firestone (Spanish); First National City Bank (Citibank) Traveler's Checks; Planters Peanuts; Shield deodorant; Swift detergent (Dutch); Seven-Up (Dutch)
  - Print advertisements, 1960s-1987 (Oversize-folder 1)
    Includes: JWT Buenos Aires 1987 (Spanish); JWT Madrid 1960s (Spanish); Reader's Digest Overseas Military Edition
  - Programa de aperfeicoamento (improvement)--Projeto Telex (Portuguese), 1986 (Box 2)
  - Programa JWT de Estagiarios (trainees) (Porguguese), 1960 (Box 2)
  - Publicity--Pavao feature in Data Market (Spanish), 1979 (Box 2)
  - Publicity--Pavao feature in Meio e Mensagem (Portuguese), 1988 (Box 8)
  - Publicity--Pavao feature in Propaganda (Portuguese), 1987 (Box 2)
  - Resignation, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Retirement and transition, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Retirement and transition--Tribute album of Pavao clippings, 1980-1988 (Box 5)
  - Retirement and transition--Tribute album Lee Pavao 30 anos J. Walter Thompson, 1988 (Box 8)
  - Seminario James Webb Young, Lima, 1985 (Box 2)
  - Strategic planners memo, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Survey--Imagem da JWT (Portuguese), 1980 (Box 2)
  - T-Shirt, 1992 (Box 7)
    Text of shirt: I found myself rumaging through the JWT Archives at Duke University and ended up having drinks and supper at Lee Pavao's, an old owl's roost, in "The Southern Part of Heaven" Chapel Hill, North Carolina, USA! September 29, 1992
  - Training program, 1980s (Box 2)
- Presentations and Speeches, 1980-1987; 2
  - Creative Forum (Spanish), 1982 (Box 2)
  - Epcot Advertising Forum, 1984; 2 folders (Box 2)
    Speeches: Jeremy Bullmore (What We Have Learned about Creating Advertising); Judie Lannon (JWT Worldwide Staff Survey); Marlene Hore (The Creative Marketplace in Target Groups); Allen Thomas (Multinational Advertising)
  - Ford presentation, 1987; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - JWT Latin America, Caracas meeting, 1980 (Box 6)
  - JWT Latin America storyboards, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Latin America Strategic Plan, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Latin American Region, 1987; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Presentation on Brazil, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Presentation on Brazil, 1982 (Box 5)
  - Presentation on Brazil, 1986 (Box 6)
  - Presentation to Board of Directors--Competitive Analysis, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Presentation to Jack Cronin, Spain, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Presentations and speeches, 1982-1985 (Box 2)
  - Promoting JWT in Latin America, 1982 (Box 2)
  - Report on Brazil, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Worldwide Operating Group (WWOG) Meeting, 1987 (Box 2)
- Photographs and Slides, 1979-1986; 3
  - Photographs, 1979-1986; 1
    - Augusto de Angelo, 1980s (Box 2)
    - Board of Directors Meeting--JWT Brazil 50th anniversary, 1979; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Contacts and negatives, Barbecue event, 1985 (Box 2)
    - Creative presentation, 1986 (Box 2)
    - Event with Don Johnston, approximately 1983 (Box 2)
    - Exhibit, Brazil, 1985 (Box 2)
    - Ford--Launch of Escort in Brazil, approximately 1980 (Box 2)
    - Group photo, 1980s (Box 2)
    - JWT Brazil office areas, 1980s (Box 2)
    - JWT Creative Forum, Rio, 1982 (Box 2)
    - JWT Latin America presentation, 1980 (Box 2)
    - Latin American Ford Supervisors Conference, 1981 (Box 2)
    - Latin American Kodak Supervisors Conference, 1983 (Box 2)
    - Latin American Managers Meeting, 1981; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Latin American Managers Meeting--Promotional merchandise items, 1984 (Box 3)
    - Latin American Unilever Supervisors Conference, 1981 (Box 3)
    - Lee Pavao 25th anniversary, 1982 (Box 3)
    - Lee Pavao at Jeca Tatu Awards, 1980 (Box 3)
      Award created by the agency Castelo Branco e Associades (CBBA) for excellence in marketing and communications in Brazil, named for Jeca Tatuzinho, a character created by author Montero Lobato in 1920 for the Fontoura Serpe e Cia firm to promote hygiene to children in the advertising for its products.
    - Lee Pavao celebration, 1981 (Box 3)
    - Lee Pavao, Kellogg International, Ford Escort, 1980s (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous, 1980s (Box 3)
    - Reception, 1982 (Box 3)
    - Staff member, 1980s (Box 3)
    - Staff with new jackets, 1980s (Box 3)
    - TDC exhibition at MASP, 1985 (Box 3)
  - Slides, 1986; 2
    - JWT Caracas, 1986 (Box 3)
    - JWT Chile, 1986 (Box 3)
    - JWT Mexico, 1986 (Box 3)
    - JWT Rio de Janeiro, 1986 (Box 3)
    - Kodak--JWT Lima, 1986 (Box 3)
    - Kodak--JWT Mexico, 1986 (Box 3)
    - Latin American creative presentation, 1986 (Box 3)
    - Latin American portfolio, 1986 (Box 3)
    - Negatives, 1980s (Box 7)
    - Presentation binder, 1986 (Box 3)
    - Presentation binder, 1986; 2 folders (Box 4)